<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title></title>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <description></description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 16 Jun 2017 01:46:35 +0800</pubDate>
    
      <item>
        <title>Clash of Civilization: notes</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/23/huntington-note.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/23/huntington-note.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;chapter-7&quot;&gt;Chapter 7&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huntington predicted so much of what happened in the Greater West (West + Russian + Islam civilizations) so successfully (9/11, Crimea, Arab Spring, migrant crisis, etc.), but the only region where he was far off track is Hong Kong and Taiwan. They didn’t continue to gravitate towards China along a straight path and have begun to form their own national identity somewhat similar to that of Japan: straddling on the fault line between East and West. Western values and Eastern culture both play significant roles. Or better yet, it’s easier to understand East Asia in the old (19c and 20c) framework, to compare China to imperial Germany and Japan instead of post-Soviet Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huntington is a Westerner after all. Although he is right that Islam and China are going to challenge the West, they are not in the same stage of history. The former is better understood in his new theory framework after the cold war, a 21c (but also an ancient) one; the latter in many ways is a continuation of what happened in the broader West from 17c to 20c. That part of the history has ended in the Greater West but not yet in the Far East.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes on why “Greater West”. This idea of the major 法统’s of this world – Charlemagne, Byzantine, Caliph, Huang Di and two lesser ones, Shah and Khan – was formulated by 刘大可. It helps to notice that three out of the four major 法统’s in the current world derive from the Roman world order and came to be the three Greater Western civilizations. The Chinese and Japanese civilizations are truly alien to the West compared to the other two.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>On Denmark</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/19/denmark.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/19/denmark.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve very gradually come to notice the fact that the Nordic countries have actually very dinstinct cultures among themselves, rendering them often on almost opposite ends of the spectra of values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of these five countries, Denmark especially arouses my interest. It ranks among the most successful nation states. (Other candidates include Switzerland and UK; the Netherlands might make it if you really stretch it. The US is completely in another category. It should be compared with empires like Rome, not other nation states.) Sweden is far from it. However, not unlike the Netherlands, the extremely basic facts such as “tolerance is not the same as indifference” about these countries are very rarely known to people who’ve never lived there. So &lt;a href=&quot;http://disq.us/p/1az3ymj&quot;&gt;this comment&lt;/a&gt; I came upon does a great job explaining such basic facts in a few words. Everyone that has at some point in their lives marveled at how good lives in Nordic countries are but doesn’t know much beyond  “much tax, much welfare, large social safety net”  should read them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here’s the full paragraph, just in case the original source becomes unavailable later:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First off, I think it should be clear that while they are Nordic, Danes, Swedes, and Norwegians have developed substantial differences in culture. To give you one example, Denmark is a relatively libertarian state, while Sweden is a more authoritarian state which evolved from a strong monarchy. To oversimplify, Danes try to solve problems through social consensus, Swedes pass laws and enforce them. So when you talk about “Nordic culture” be careful not to think of them the same way.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My impression (from visits with my Danish relatives) is that any advantages Danes might have flow from culture and not laws or structures. From what I’ve seen, Danes tend to be less materialistic and more family and community oriented on average than I’ve seen in the U.S. But perhaps the biggest difference is the notion of “social responsibility” that pervades the culture. Danes feel it is important to work primarily because they should be contributing to society, while in the U.S. work tends to also revolve around identity, social position, and goods. Danes also typically don’t have problem with their expensive social net, because they feel that it won’t be abused because that would be the wrong thing to do. It’s really these types of attitudes that have enabled Denmark to maintain a libertarian character while also retaining a strong social net.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I can understand why many of my Danish relatives wouldn’t think of leaving Denmark, even with the perennially crummy weather. It would not be an economist’s way of running a country (too many taxes, too many holidays, not enough crazy entrepreneurs and overly hard workers), but it provides enough for a society that is much less materialistic than ours. To give you an example, one of my uncles is a VP of Sales at an appliance manufacturer, but he is quite happy in his 1500 square foot one story with a modest yard in the suburbs of Copenhagen. And from what he told me this seemed pretty common and they were quite happy with what they had.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Danes have a high degree of social tolerance, although I think this may be tested as Denmark gets more immigrants. In part, I think this is because nearly all Danes live within 100 miles of another country, frequently speak a few languages (my cousins had to learn 3 languages to graduate from high school) and typically have traveled through a number of countries. But part of it is probably is because Danes have a pretty common set of social values as well.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;I don’t think it makes sense to try and emulate Denmark too much. We have a different culture, one that is more heterogeneous and dynamic than Denmark’s. But I do wish we could get a healthy dose of some of the Danish values about tolerance, the importance of family and community, and less emphasis on material things. But in the end each culture has its different values and histories, and therefore it should come up with its own unique solutions and only use those solutions from other societies that fit its culture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interesting thought: the Danish values about family, education etc. mentioned here remind you of East Asians, don’t they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, this idea of “social cohesion”, a certain empathy/”tender link”/common interests and values between the ruling elites and the common people, sounds very empty but more than a few people that have lived in Nordic countries say it’s obviously tangible, alive and real. Although some claim that this cohesion has also shown the trend of being slowly eroded over the decades.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Diary 20170216</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/16/diary.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/02/16/diary.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sviatoslav Richter is officially my favorite pianist now. Gives me chills every time I listen to him. E.g. &lt;a href=&quot;https://itun.es/us/AsF7x?i=401470629&quot;&gt;this final movement of Beethoven Sonata No. 23 (Appassionata)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1702.03976&quot;&gt;This paper by Das Sarma&lt;/a&gt; is such a refreshing breath of free air in our field filled with such a large amount of bullshit doublespeak euphemism perpetrated by almost all groups in the community but especially CPH who try every far-fetched way to explain their data in the Majorana picture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;We urge materials science efforts toward the fabrication of optimal hybrid structures using better parent superconductors in order to avoid the problems of small and soft topological gaps and strongly renormalized low-energy nanowire spectra that plague the current experimental systems. In particular, the soft topological gap is a very serious problem because a hybrid system with a soft gap is, strictly speaking, gapless or, at best, can be characterized by some small ‘effective gap’. Since the size of the gap itself defines the strength of the topological protection, a small and/or soft topological gap will prevent non-Abelian braiding from being successful in semiconductor wire-superconductor structures, even if Majorana zero modes are localized at the wire ends. In our opinion, this is the most important problem preventing further experimental progress in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;This work is supported by Microsoft, LPS-MPO-CMTC, and NSF DMR-1414683&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, essentially, “Cut your BS. The things we have now won’t give us any ‘topological protection’ and won’t lead to braiding or topological quantum computation, no matter what you call them, Majorana or otherwise.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On American politics. The USA is clearly going through a constitutional crisis now given what’s been happening in the past few weeks after Donald Trump has been sworn in as the new president. According to the NPR Politics interview last night (Feb 15th), the current situation in Washington is a “train wreck”. Seems this era will be remembered by history as a major event the significance of which is at least on the same level with the Andrew Jackson presidency, and maybe on par with FDR or even getting close to Lincoln.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My hope before the election was for Donald Trump to win, but not because I liked him – quite the contrary. I only hoped so because of this single belief: if Hillary Clinton wins, she will be more or less a continuation along the same path America has been on for decades, which has clearly not been working out well in recent years and has fostered some dark, extreme discontent among the angry white men. This dark mood has been growing at a staggering speed in the Obama years and will continue to do so in the next four if Hillary wins. If you find what you see now abhorrent, it will only get orders of magnitude worse after being suppressed for four more years. I.e., it is this single judgment I heard that led to me hoping this way: “Trump is not the Gracchi. But if you elect Hillary Clinton, there’s a high chance the real Gracchi will appear in 2020. &lt;em&gt;That&lt;/em&gt; will genuinely signal the demise of American democracy.” Or to put it in other words, “those who find themselves too virtuous to bend their knees and collaborate with Chiang Kai Shek will be taught how to behave by Mao; Trump is not an extremist like Mao after all”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore I hoped for Trump getting elected but then shortly after getting impeached for outrageous behaviors. This will serve as a “pressure release” process for the resentment accumulated among a lot of Americans. After all, given how strong the one million bureaucrats collectivevly in the Washington establishment are, he would either have to behave and find a way to navigate among them, or overreach too far and get stopped by the other power branches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So indeed, I foresaw that Trump will test how strong the immune system of American politics is (i.e. the “checks and balances”). However, before the test really start to take shape, I didn’t have an idea how ugly it would look. When your immune system is tested, even by a common flu, the body will inevitably feel pretty terrible. Also, I didn’t fully grasp how authoritarian Trump is. A virus is a virus, after all. Even vaccines sometimes cause symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what really disappoints me now is that the response of the immune system comes not from the power branches I (and I believe a lot of other people) expected: the Congress is completely controlled by Republicans so there’s very little resistance from that side; Democrats, the media and hardcore left wingers are descending into this madness where they oppose everything Trump says and does and eventually discredit themselves entirely; the judiciary branch indeed starts to counter the acts of Trump on the Muslim ban but is regarded as a manifestation of the partisanship of judges now, which will only intensify the role politics plays in the courts and further harm the credibility of the judicial system. We could also look at this from a broader perspective: the Congress has been weakened a lot by the ever-increasing power of the “imperial presidency” after FDR; the judiciary system has been more and more politicized and are beginning to lose the trust of the public and their utmost authority; the “Fourth Power”, the media, is becoming obsolete day by day after the rise of social media. Now who’s the most effective in stopping presidential overreach?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer turns out to be not anyone the Founding Fathers wanted it to be – the intelligence community. CIA and the like. Washington bureaucrats. The opposite of an open society. The agencies that were founded largely in response to and as a mirror image of Soviet espionage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;America has stared too long into the abyss, fought too long with the dragon and found its soul corrupted by them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This time I really smell decline. Without any doubt and confirmed by so many other observers independently, America is in the late stage of the Roman Republic. The days of Trajan and Hadrian, the “most happy and prosperous age of humanity” are yet to come, but the times of infinite possibilities unimaginable to all but the divine are gone.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 16 Feb 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>西方中心論</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/15/western-centrism.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/01/15/western-centrism.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/western-centrism.png&quot; alt=&quot;「西方中心論」&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;圖片出自 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.goodreads.com/book/show/282085.Human_Accomplishment&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Human Accomplishment: The Pursuit of Excellence in the Arts and Sciences, 800 B.C. to 1950&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 第 252 頁。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;數學教會人認識指數和對數，了不起的成就。面對指數增長，容易失去格局感，此時用百分比或者比值來衡量不再是良好的方式，而應該對數回去理解它。比如你可以說一句完全正確的話叫做「人類歷史上 98% 以上的晶體管被生產於最近五年」，聽起來有點怪異，但這不過是摩爾定律（單芯片集成度指數增長）與芯片總產量增長的自然推論，無非是 &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;2^n/2^{n+5}\approx 0.03&lt;/script&gt; 這樣平凡的計算的自然語言描述。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;同樣的，工業革命/科學革命是一個科學和技術指數進步的過程。我們一切試圖量化人類技術水平發展歷史的嘗試都會不可避免地得出結論：最近幾百年的人類技術進步大致符合指數增長曲線（比如上圖）。那麼「人類文明 97% 由歐美白人男性創造」這種結論也與「97% 的晶體管生產於最近五年」一樣平凡——它是「指數增長」這個包含了更多信息的判斷的自然推論。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我們在示波器上看信號的 FFT 時、畫頻率響應曲線時一般都會用對數座標，否則你會只看到在某個點上有個峯值，其他的所有細節全被淹沒完了，成了零附近的不到 1 像素大的噪音般的波動（上）：&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://static1.squarespace.com/static/5230e9f8e4b06ab69d1d8068/t/570d6afee32140b109e4c398/1460497158632/?format=500w&quot; alt=&quot;Why dB scale&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;顯然當切換成對數座標（下）之後，我們才能更清楚地理解頻譜的成分。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;同樣的，開頭那張圖有不同的理解方式：線性座標可以強調「指數增長」有多麼超出人類對數字的直觀經驗——與技術革命開始後取得的成果比，一切技術革命前的成果都微不足道，少到可以忽略；如果你切換到對數座標，則可以看到比如歐洲曾經領先，但在公元 500 年到 1400 年左右出現了大低谷，而亞洲大陸在此期間碩果累累。甚至時間再往前推一點還可以看到在工業革命之前大約一萬年還有過農業革命，那同樣是一次改變人類歷史的重大事件，但如果你用線性座標那麼農業革命前後的生產力進步會成爲小到根本看不到的幾個點。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;指數增長通常是正反饋的結果（&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;dy/dt\propto y&lt;/script&gt;），而正反饋的形成需要一些可能相當苛刻甚至偶然的條件，當所有條件滿足之後開啓正反饋過程，當響應強到正反饋循環被破壞時指數增長結束。所以合適的理解方式是類似於看頻響曲線那樣：歷史一般不是始終在線性進步，而是有若干次指數增長，每次指數增長前後社會都有着本質的不同。而指數增長不是普遍規律，不是隨時都在發生，需要不知道哪天天時地利人和都恰好湊齊了纔會發生一次。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「西方創造了幾乎所有人類物質文明」是一種非常反直觀的敘述，然而這只不過說明人類需要藉助對數這一工具才能理解指數過程。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 15 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fractured Lands</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/12/fractured-lands.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/01/12/fractured-lands.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;從家裏回來的飛機上終於看完了紐約時報的長篇報道 &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2016/08/11/magazine/isis-middle-east-arab-spring-fractured-lands.html?_r=1&quot;&gt;Fractured Lands: How The Arab World Came Apart&lt;/a&gt;。除了渾身冷汗，沒有別的感覺。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;當時飛機也正穿越（其實是繞過）這片土地的上空，從悶熱潮溼的迪拜起飛沿着波斯灣上空到達幼發拉底、底格里斯河口（那真是個窄窄的海灣，一路上可以從窗口看見海岸），卻沒有繼續進入伊拉克領空而是從伊朗上空繞着邊境飛過，然後穿過土耳其東部來到黑海，進入歐洲。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/dxb-to-ams.png&quot; alt=&quot;中東上空航線&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;起初飛到兩河沖積平原上空時，平靜的藍色海面變成了平整的黃色土地。後來地上開始出現一排排的褶皺，然後整齊排列的山脈越來越高，直到雪線出現，山頂開始被越來越多的白色覆蓋。進入歐洲不久後，身下便被厚密的雲層覆蓋，沒看到大地。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;我沒甚麼結論或者感慨好說。唯一能說的是：去讀那篇報道。這片土地如此多災多難，因爲它是人類文明的故鄉，它六千年來始終是（或十分接近）風暴的中心。那篇報道（和傳統智慧）將中東命定悲劇的起點劃在一戰，然而正如評論所言，Fracture 在此地遠比 20 世紀久遠。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「已有的事後必再有，已行的事後必再行」（傳道書 1:9），Raqqa 何嘗不是今日的莫斯科或者延安。一年多以前我甚至不知道敘利亞內戰是甚麼，而這六個個體的故事在不斷地確認着這一年多以來我看到的關於這片土地最陰暗最殘忍的描述，無情地向我宣告：你知道，那些冷血而讓你痛苦的保守主義者是對的，錯誤的問題沒有正確的答案。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fractured lands 就是霍布斯筆下的自然狀態。據說俄羅斯建國前當地也是如此，而莫斯科公國成功加冕爲利維坦，結束了那個時代。「文明世界」的人們當然可以隨手指出利維坦作的一百種惡，然而看到如今的中東，或許就會明白「終結自然狀態」已經是莫大的善。歷史並不允許每次以衝突劃定邊界的過程都以民族國家的形成結束，甚至這個過程可能不會結束。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;歷史遠沒有終結。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>《魔笛》</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2017/01/04/die-zauberflote.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2017/01/04/die-zauberflote.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;哲学家民族的童话史诗&quot;&gt;哲学家民族的童话史诗&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;德意志民族真是几百年下来一点都没变，纯洁的抽象概念大于浑浊的具体经验，最纯洁的理念尽头有着乌托邦（另一头是地狱），而「黑暗/邪恶」是我们通向纯洁乌托邦的障碍，通过 struggle 除掉这些阻碍之后 Heaven on Earth 即可实现。二战前后看似民族性格的彻底调头也不过是概念的指代对象变了，「黑暗/邪恶」的化身从犹太人变成了 bigots，这套叙事根本没变，那种被摩尼教影响过的中世纪天主教上帝—撒旦二元论。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;莫扎特用他的那种天真甚至幼稚的音乐风格掩盖了歌剧的史诗性。此前听/看都不曾看字幕、看好的制作，很容易就被音乐本身欺骗。这是个严肃而丰富庞杂的故事，多主题/母题。除上述犹太–基督教/德国古典哲学母题之外，也有像《尼伯龙根的指环》等一样的日耳曼森林童话、中世纪社会生态种种（才明白美国大学里天天聚众淫乱的兄弟会原来和本剧中神殿的来源一样，是共济会等中世纪行会组织）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;音乐本身当然也极美，莫扎特是旋律大师，而晚期受了巴赫影响之后真是古典风格的畏人高峰。我一直仅能喜欢晚期的莫扎特，《安魂曲》和《魔笛》中一些段落都极其复调，后者的男童三重唱仿佛圣咏。以及理解了「纯洁的理念」之后，开始明白德国人喜欢搞的 Leitmotif 这套东西到底是为什么。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>EBPG CAD</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/08/25/EBPG-CAD.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/08/25/EBPG-CAD.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;ebpg-commands-quick-lookup&quot;&gt;EBPG commands quick lookup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;0-transfer-dxf-file-to-tu-delft-server&quot;&gt;0. Transfer &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.DXF&lt;/code&gt; file to TU Delft server&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protocol: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SFTP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;sftp.tudelft.nl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Username: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NetID&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Password: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NetID password&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;1-transfer-dxf-file-to-pegasus&quot;&gt;1. Transfer &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.DXF&lt;/code&gt; file to Pegasus&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protocol: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SFTP&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pegasus.kavli.tudelft.nl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Username: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cad&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Password: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;KN-lab&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;2-use-layout-beamer-on-pegasus-to-export-to-gpf-files&quot;&gt;2. Use Layout Beamer on Pegasus to export to GPF files&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protocol: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SSH&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pegasus.kavli.tudelft.nl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Username: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cad&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Password: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&amp;amp;KN-lab&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;LB&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Import DXF -&amp;gt; Extract (one layer each) -&amp;gt; Heal (resolve overlay in patterns) -&amp;gt; Export&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Export&lt;/strong&gt;: estimate the &lt;em&gt;beam step size&lt;/em&gt; according to the desired &lt;em&gt;beam spot size&lt;/em&gt; for each layer as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\text{step size} = \text{spot size}/1.5&lt;/script&gt; (resolution=beam step size).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beam spot sizes of each beam can be found by logging onto the EBPG computer and use command &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;fegmode estimate&lt;/code&gt;. E.g. for pads we can use the largest beam spot size. On EBPG5200 this is 132nm so we can set the beam step size to be 88nm (=132nm/1.5). Similarly we can use the 30nm beam for coarse features (and thus 20nm step size) and for the smallest fine features we can set the beam step size to be 2nm and use the 3nm beam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;putp&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;putp5200&lt;/code&gt; to transfer the &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GPF&lt;/code&gt; files to the EBPG computer. Use the wild card to save time in the following way:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;putp5k 20160824\*.gpf
putp5200 20160824\*.gpf
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will transfer all &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;GPF&lt;/code&gt; files with names beginning with &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;20160824&lt;/code&gt; to the old EBPG.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;3-use-cjob-on-the-ebpg-computers&quot;&gt;3. Use &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CJOB&lt;/code&gt; on the EBPG computers&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Protocol: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;SSH&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Server: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;epic-beta.kavli.tudelft.nl&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;epic-alfa.kavli.tudelft.nl&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Username: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pg&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Password: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pg5200@Delft&lt;/code&gt; / &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;pg5000@Delft&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Command: &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;cjob&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open an example &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;CJOB&lt;/code&gt; file and modify the corresponding parts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For each &lt;em&gt;exposure&lt;/em&gt; we specify four markers. For different exposures different markers should be used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be sure to select the correct file, beam and dose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally export each exposure as a &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;.job&lt;/code&gt; file.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;4-things-to-check&quot;&gt;4. Things to check&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Specify markers to use for &lt;em&gt;both exposures  and patterns (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;gpf&lt;/code&gt;’s)&lt;/em&gt;. And they must be the same.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The exposure marker type is &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;measure map&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Select &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;Keystones&lt;/code&gt; in the pattern marker specification.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 25 Aug 2016 07:14:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Non-equilibrium notes</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Nonequilibrium-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Nonequilibrium-notes.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;langevin-equation&quot;&gt;Langevin equation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Brownian motion can be described by the Langevin equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m\frac{dv}{dt}(t)=-\gamma v(t) + F(t) + R(t)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; is the familiar “damping” rate in the dynamic equation of oscillators. It represents a “dragging” force by the particles near it slowing it down. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R(t)&lt;/script&gt; is a “random kick” to the particle. It is a Gaussian random variable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt; R(t)\right&gt; =0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;R(t)R(t+\tau)\right&gt;=q \delta(\tau) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
P(R)=\frac{1}{\sqrt{2\pi\left&lt;R^2\right&gt;}}\exp\left(-\frac{R^2}{2\left&lt;R^2\right&gt;}\right) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F=0&lt;/script&gt;, the solution to the Langevin equation is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;v(t)=v(0)e^{-\frac{\gamma t}{m}} + \frac{1}{m} \int_0^t e^{-\frac{\gamma(t-\tau)}{m}}R(\tau)d\tau&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And the average value of the above expression is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;v(t)\right&gt; =v(0)e^{-\frac{\gamma t}{m}} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The expectation value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v^2(t)&lt;/script&gt; is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;v^2(t)\right&gt; = v_0^2 e^{-\frac{2\gamma t}{m}}+\frac{q}{2\gamma m}\left(1-e^{-\frac{2\gamma t}{m}}\right) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For large &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt;, it reduces to&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;v^2(\infty)\right&gt; =\frac{q}{2\gamma m} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the &lt;strong&gt;equipartition&lt;/strong&gt; theorem we also know &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;v^2\right&gt;=k_B T/m %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, so&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;q=2\gamma k_B T&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Velocity autocorrelation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;v(t)v(t+\tau)\right&gt; = \left&lt;v^2(0)\right&gt; e^{-\frac{\gamma \vert \tau\vert }{m}} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Position:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;x^2(t)\right&gt;=2\left&lt;v^2\right&gt; \frac m\gamma \left[t+\frac m \gamma \left(e^{-\frac{\gamma t}{m}}-1\right)\right] %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For large &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt;, take the exponential term to be 0. Compare that result with the diffusion behavior &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;x^2(t)\right&gt;=2Dt %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, we get the &lt;strong&gt;Einstein relation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
D=\left&lt;v^2\right&gt; \frac m\gamma = \frac{k_B T}{\gamma} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Fick’s law&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;j_\text{diff} = -D\nabla \rho (\mathbf{r},t)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;j_\text{diff}&lt;/script&gt; is the flux due to diffusion, and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rho&lt;/script&gt; is the particle density. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;D&lt;/script&gt; is the diffusion constant above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When stationary, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{v}=\mathbf{F}/\gamma&lt;/script&gt;, thus the drift flux due to a driving force is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;j_\text{drift}= \rho(\mathbf{r},t)\mathbf{v}(\mathbf{r},t) =\rho(\mathbf{r},t)\frac{\mathbf{F}(\mathbf{r},t)}{\gamma}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Continuity equation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial}{\partial t}\rho (\mathbf{r},t) +\nabla \cdot j_\text{total}(\mathbf{r},t)=0&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F=0&lt;/script&gt;, use the continuity equation and Fick’s law to get the &lt;strong&gt;diffusion equation&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial \rho}{\partial t} =\nabla \cdot (D\nabla \rho)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fokker-Planck equation: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;P\propto \rho&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial P}{\partial t}=\gamma v\frac{\partial P}{\partial v} + \gamma k_B T \frac{\partial^2 P}{\partial v^2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stationary condition &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\partial P/\partial t=0&lt;/script&gt; will lead to the Maxwell distribution:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;P\propto e^{-\frac{mv^2}{2k_B T}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;wiener-kintchine-theorem&quot;&gt;Wiener-Kintchine theorem&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A(t)&lt;/script&gt; is a time-dependent random variable. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K(s)&lt;/script&gt; is the &lt;strong&gt;autocorrelation function&lt;/strong&gt;, defined as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
K(s) \equiv \left&lt;A(t)A(t+s)\right&gt; = \lim_{T\rightarrow \infty} \frac{1}{T} \int_0^T A(t)A(t+s)dt %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It has the property &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;K(s)=K(-s)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Fourier transform of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A(t)&lt;/script&gt; is&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\tilde{A} (\omega) = \frac{1}{\sqrt{T}}\int_0^T A(t)e^{i\omega t}dt&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(from now on taking the limit &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T\rightarrow \infty&lt;/script&gt; is implicitly assumed.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;strong&gt;spectral density&lt;/strong&gt; is defined as&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
S(\omega)=\left&lt;\tilde{A}(\omega) \tilde{A}^*(\omega) \right&gt; %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wiener-Kintchine theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: the autocorrelation and spectral density are Fourier transform pairs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;S(\omega)=\int_{-\frac{T}{2}}^\frac{T}{2} K(s)e^{-i\omega s}ds \equiv \tilde{K}(\omega)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apply it to the Langevin equation. Let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R(t)&lt;/script&gt; be a non-Gaussian random variable&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;R(t_1)R(t_2)\right&gt;=K_F(t_2-t_1) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using the equipartition theorem we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\tilde{K}_F(0)=2\gamma k_B T&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;v(0)v(t)\right&gt;=\frac{k_B T}{m}e^{-\frac{\gamma \vert t\vert }{m}} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The power spectrum is then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;\vert v(\omega)\vert ^2\right&gt; = \frac{2k_B T}{\gamma}\frac{1}{1+\left(\frac{\omega m}{\gamma}\right)^2} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Mean Field Approximation notes</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Mean-field-approximation-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Mean-field-approximation-notes.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Ising model Hamiltonian:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
H=-K\sum_{&lt;ij&gt;}s_i s_j - h\sum_i s_i %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mean-field-approximation&quot;&gt;Mean Field Approximation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;derivation-of-mean-field-hamiltonian&quot;&gt;Derivation of Mean Field Hamiltonian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use a &lt;strong&gt;global macroscopic&lt;/strong&gt; ensemble average &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=\langle \sum_i s_i \rangle/N&lt;/script&gt; to approximate the &lt;strong&gt;microscopic&lt;/strong&gt; surrounding environment of each site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
H=-K\sum_{&lt;ij&gt;} (m+\delta s_i)(m+\delta s_j) - h\sum_i s_i %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abandon the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\sum \delta s_i \delta s_j&lt;/script&gt; terms because they are second-order infinitesimals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
H\approx -K\sum_{&lt;ij&gt;} m(\delta s_i+\delta s_j) - K\sum_{&lt;ij&gt;}m^2 - h\sum_i s_i %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Revert to notation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta s_i \equiv s_i-m&lt;/script&gt; again. Let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q&lt;/script&gt; be the number of nearest neighbors each site has (e.g. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q=2^d&lt;/script&gt; for square lattices, where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; is the dimension). Note that there are &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;qN/2&lt;/script&gt; pairs of nearest neighbors in total. Thus &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\sum_{&lt;ij&gt;} s_i=\frac{q}{2}\sum_i s_i %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\therefore H_\text{MFA}=-(Kqm+h)\sum_i s_i +\frac12 NKqm^2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is our mean field Hamiltonian.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;mean-field-partition-function-and-free-energy&quot;&gt;Mean field partition function and free energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{aligned}Z_\text{MFA}&amp;=\sum_{\{s_i=\pm1\}} e^{-\beta H_\text{MFA}}=e^{-\frac12 \beta KNqm^2} \prod_i \sum_{s_i=\pm1}e^{\beta (Kqm+h)s_i} \\ &amp;=e^{-\frac12 \beta KNqm^2} 2^N \cosh^N \beta(Kqm+h)\end{aligned} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\begin{aligned}F_\text{MFA}/N&amp;=-\frac{k_B T}{N}\ln Z_\text{MFA} \\ &amp;=\frac{Kqm^2}{2} -k_B T\ln [2\cosh \beta(Kqm+h)]\end{aligned} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; is not in fact a parameter here. If the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; parameters &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T, K, h&lt;/script&gt; are fixed, then &lt;em&gt;they determine what value &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; is!&lt;/em&gt; (Remember the definition of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; – it’s an ensemble average.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;self-consistency-relation&quot;&gt;Self-consistency relation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We haven’t figured out the value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; yet. This is done by solving a self-consistency equation, because the expression used to obtain &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; (the partition function) contains &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; itself. There are two (similar) ways to obtain the self-consistency relation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we can make use of the MFA Hamiltonian above:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m=\frac{1}{N}\langle \sum_i s_i \rangle=\frac{1}{N} \sum_i \langle s_i \rangle = \langle s_i \rangle&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\therefore m=\frac{\sum_{s_i=\pm 1}s_i e^{\beta (Kqm+h)s_i}}{\sum_{s_i=\pm 1} e^{\beta (Kqm+h)s_i}}=\tanh \beta (Kqm+h)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The summation extends only to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s_i&lt;/script&gt; because everything else factors out and cancels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second (easier) way is to start from the original Ising Hamiltonian, and separate it into two parts: terms containing &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s_i&lt;/script&gt; (which we denote by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H_i&lt;/script&gt; and terms that do not contain &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s_i&lt;/script&gt; (which we denote as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H_{0i}&lt;/script&gt;). Obviously &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
H_i=-K\sum_{&lt;j&gt;}s_i s_j - h s_i %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; where the sum is over the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q&lt;/script&gt; nearest neighbors of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt;. Next, neglect the fluctuations of the surrounding environment: replace each &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s_j&lt;/script&gt; with a global average &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt;. Now &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H_i \approx -(Kqm+h)s_i&lt;/script&gt;. We then proceed to write out &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;Z&lt;/script&gt; and note that the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e^{-\beta H_{0i}}&lt;/script&gt; contributions factor out and cancel each other and what’s left is easily shown to be the same expression as above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is the self-consistency relation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m=\tanh \beta(Kqm+h)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solving this equation (numerically) will tell us the value of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h=0&lt;/script&gt;, it becomes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m=\tanh \beta Kqm&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equation has either one or three solutions. The separating point between these two is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta Kq=1&lt;/script&gt;, when &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y=x&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y=\tanh \beta Kqx&lt;/script&gt; are tangent to each other at the origin. This is the critical point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{Kq}{k_B T_c}=1&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;, there is only one solution &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=0&lt;/script&gt;. Below &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;, there are three solutions but &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=0&lt;/script&gt; is unstable (a local maximum, as we will see later in the Landau theory). The positive and negative values are the two symmetrical values &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; can assume with no preference over any one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/B=0.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As shown in the plot, at the critical point, there is a clear “sudden change” (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\partial m/\partial h&lt;/script&gt; is discontinuous), i.e. phase transition. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; itself is a derivative of the free energy &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F&lt;/script&gt;, so this is a second-order phase transition. If we gradually lower the temperature from above &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt; to below &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;, since there are two equally favored states, the system will spontaneously enter one of them. This is a &lt;strong&gt;spontaneous symmetry breaking&lt;/strong&gt;. It is often associated with &lt;strong&gt;degenerate ground states&lt;/strong&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=\pm1&lt;/script&gt; are perfectly symmetric when &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T=0&lt;/script&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h\ne 0&lt;/script&gt;, there is no phase transition. Although in some cases there are three roots of the self-consistency equation, the middel one is still unstable and the one that has an opposite sign of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt; is &lt;em&gt;metastable&lt;/em&gt;. In Landau theory, it’s a local minimum but higher than the other global minumum. It wants to flip its sign and assume the true stable value if opportunity arises. (But note that if this flip occurs, e.g. when we raise temperature so that the metastable root is no longer there and we only have one stable root, this is a 1st order phase transition because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; itself is discontinuous.) We plot &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; under different values of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mid h \mid&lt;/script&gt; and see that indeed there is no “sudden change”. (The upper curve is the stable value for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&gt;0&lt;/script&gt; and the lower curve for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
h&lt;0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/B=1e-3.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/B=1e-1.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/B=10.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stable and metastable states under the same &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&gt;0&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/metastable.svg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;critical-exponents&quot;&gt;Critical exponents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are 6 critical exponents: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha, \beta, \gamma, \delta,\nu, \eta&lt;/script&gt;. We can obtain the first four from the MFA method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;t\equiv (T-T_c)/T_c&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;alpha-heat-capacity&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt;: heat capacity&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C\propto \frac{\partial^2 F}{\partial t^2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C \propto t^{-\alpha}&lt;/script&gt; near &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We already have the mean field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F&lt;/script&gt;. Use that to differentiate twice w.r.t &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; and we will see that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C \propto&lt;/script&gt; constant, i.e. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha=0&lt;/script&gt;. This can be done much more easily later using the Landau theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;beta-m-and-temperature&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt;: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; and temperature&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m\propto \vert t\vert^{\beta}&lt;/script&gt; near &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt; (but below it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Use the self-consistenty relation and Taylor expand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tanh x \approx x-x^3/3&lt;/script&gt; because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m \rightarrow 0&lt;/script&gt;. Then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m=\beta Kqm-\frac{(\beta Kqm)^3}{3}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solve for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; and note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1=\beta_c Kq&lt;/script&gt;. We obtain &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m^2\propto (\beta-\beta_c) \propto (T_c-T)&lt;/script&gt;. So &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta=1/2&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;delta-m-and-h&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta&lt;/script&gt;: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m\propto h^{\delta}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are &lt;em&gt;critical exponents&lt;/em&gt;, we only care about temperatures near criticality. Since there is no criticality for nonzero &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt;, we directly set &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T=T_c&lt;/script&gt; i.e. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta Kq=1&lt;/script&gt; : &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=\tanh (m+\beta h)&lt;/script&gt;. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\therefore \tanh^{-1} m =m+\beta h&lt;/script&gt;. Next Taylor expand &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\tanh^{-1}&lt;/script&gt; and it’s easily seen that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m^3\propto h&lt;/script&gt;. So &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta=1/3&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;gamma-partial-mpartial-h-and-t&quot;&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt;: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\partial m/\partial h&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Susceptibility &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi \propto \frac{\partial m}{\partial h} \big\vert_{h=0}\propto t^{-\gamma}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T\rightarrow T_c&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h\rightarrow 0&lt;/script&gt; both from above. Take the derivative over &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt; in the original self-consistency relation. Note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=0&lt;/script&gt; for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;. We can show that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi \propto t^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;, so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu=1&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;switching-to-landau-theory&quot;&gt;Switching to Landau theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, it’s quite hard to obtain &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; from the MFA directly, and downright impossible to get &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\eta&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu&lt;/script&gt;. However in the upcoming Landau theory, we only need to obtain an expression for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt; and show that the parameter there has &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0 \propto t&lt;/script&gt;, and then &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt; can be calculated easily. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\eta&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu&lt;/script&gt; takes more work and the Landau-Ginzburg theory must be used for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, Landau theory is equivalent to MFA and they both yield not so good (although indeed the same) results for lower dimensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;why-does-mfa-fail-miserably-for-1-2-and-3-dimensions&quot;&gt;Why does MFA fail miserably for 1, 2, and 3 dimensions?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because we used a macroscopic average to replace the interaction between a particular site and its nearest neighbors. In higher dimension, each site has many neighbors and the overall interaction between it and those neighbors will be quite close to the global average value. But in lower dimensions, each site has very few neighbors and the fluctuations can cause the real scenario to deviate from a macroscopic average dramatically.&lt;/p&gt;

</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Landau-Ginzburg notes</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Landau-Ginzburg-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Landau-Ginzburg-notes.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;MFA &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rightarrow&lt;/script&gt; (treat &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; as if it’s a real parameter) &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rightarrow&lt;/script&gt; Landau &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rightarrow&lt;/script&gt; (let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; vary with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;) &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\rightarrow&lt;/script&gt; Landau-Ginzburg&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;landau-theory&quot;&gt;Landau theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although we said in the MFA notes that the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; in the MFA free energy is not a real parameter but a fixed number under given &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt;, let us now pretend it is a real &lt;em&gt;free&lt;/em&gt; variable as if it can assume any value independent of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T,h&lt;/script&gt; and treat this &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; more seriously.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;landau-free-energy&quot;&gt;Landau free energy&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we assume &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; is a free variable, we can Taylor expand the free energy in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt;, for the moment up until the 4th power:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;f(m)=-hm+r_0 m^2 + um^4&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h=0&lt;/script&gt;, only even powers survive because of the symmetry of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-m&lt;/script&gt; in the Ising model and its free energy as an even function of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently we don’t need to know the specific form of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt;. We only need to know they are the Taylor coefficients of whatever function of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; the free energy is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next see graphs for what this function looks like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/Landau.png&quot; alt=&quot;Landau free energy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt; is always positive We first look at what happens when &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h=0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
r_0&lt;0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f(m)&lt;/script&gt; has two minima and one local maximum.  These are exactly the three roots we got from the self-consistency relation in MFA. The local maximum is an unstable point. The system will only reside around the two minima, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\pm m_0&lt;/script&gt;. This corresponds to the case of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
T&lt;T_c %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&gt;0&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f(m)&lt;/script&gt; has only one minimum at &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=0&lt;/script&gt;. This is the only root we got from the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=\tanh \beta Kqm&lt;/script&gt; relation. This case corresponds to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0=0&lt;/script&gt;, this is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T=T_c&lt;/script&gt;. Although we still have only one minimum, the region around this minimum is very flat (the first three orders of derivatives are all 0). This means the system can travel left and right along the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; axis without paying much price in free energy increase. This suggests that the system fluctuates heavily around the average at critical temperature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
m_0=\begin{cases}0, \quad r_0 \propto (T-T_c)\ge 0 \\ \pm \sqrt{-\frac{r_0}{2u}}, \quad r_0 \propto (T-T_c) &lt;0  \end{cases} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then we look at what happens if &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h\ne 0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/Landau with B.png&quot; alt=&quot;Landau with B&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we know what “metastable” means: the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
h&gt;0,m&lt;0 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; solution is a local minimum but not a global minimum. It will jump to the global minimum whenever fluctuation gives it enough energy to cross the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m=0&lt;/script&gt; wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;critical-exponents-betaalphagamma&quot;&gt;Critical exponents &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta,\alpha,\gamma&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We stated above &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0\propto (T-T_c)&lt;/script&gt;, but why? Because below &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;, we know from above that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0&lt;/script&gt; approaches 0 as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0=\sqrt{-r_0/(2u)}&lt;/script&gt;. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;u&lt;/script&gt; is positive (actually it doesn’t vary with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T&lt;/script&gt; to the first order), so the rate of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0&lt;/script&gt; approaching 0 in the first order is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0\propto (-r_0)^{1/2}&lt;/script&gt;. Since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt; is a parameter that’s determined by temperature and we have shown in the previous MFA derivation that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0 \propto (-t)^{1/2}&lt;/script&gt; below &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T_c&lt;/script&gt;, so we immediately recognize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;r_0 \propto t=\frac{T-T_c}{T_c}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is very helpful for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can very conveniently know:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C\propto \frac{\partial^2 f}{\partial t^2} \propto \frac{\partial ^2}{\partial t^2}r_0 = \text{constant}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha=0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\chi \propto \frac{\partial m}{\partial h}=\left(\frac{\partial h}{\partial m}\right)^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be obtained by letting &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\partial f /\partial m&lt;/script&gt; with a nonzero &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt; and then showing that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\partial h}{\partial m_0}=2r_0+4um_0^2\propto t+\text{const}&lt;/script&gt;, so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi\propto t^{-1}&lt;/script&gt;, and thus &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma=1&lt;/script&gt;. This is much simpler than using the original MFA expression directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;landau-ginzburg-theory&quot;&gt;Landau-Ginzburg theory&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Landau to Landau-Ginzburg, we only make one crucial change: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; is no longer a global parameter that assumes the same value for the entire lattice, but we now let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; vary with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;, i.e., &lt;em&gt;it assumes different values at different places on the lattice&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we have  a quantity &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt;, which means the average spin in a region &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Omega&lt;/script&gt; around the position &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;. This region &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\Omega&lt;/script&gt; is &lt;em&gt;“macroscopically small, microscopically large”&lt;/em&gt;, meaning that each region is large enough to contain many spin sites and  have an average value taking any real value between &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;[-1,1]&lt;/script&gt;, and also small enough for us to use a continuous &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt; to label their positions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;hamiltonian&quot;&gt;Hamiltonian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;H=\int [k(\nabla m)^2 +r_0 m(\mathbf{r})^2 + u m(\mathbf{r})^4+h(\mathbf{r})m(\mathbf{r})]d^d\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new Hamiltonian, besides being an integral over space, differs from the Landau Hamiltonian by a term &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k(\nabla m)^2&lt;/script&gt;. This term means that we have energy penalty for  making the average spin of two neighboring regions different – if two neighboring regions are “all up + all down”, it should have a greater energy than the case “all up + all up”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An immediate use of this new Hamiltonian is to solve the “domain wall” model in 1D. See David Tong’s notes for more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;correlation-function&quot;&gt;Correlation function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g(\mathbf{r_i},\mathbf{r_j})\equiv\langle m(\mathbf{r_i})m(\mathbf{r_j})\rangle -  \langle m(\mathbf{r_i})\rangle \langle m(\mathbf{r_j})\rangle&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The average notations here mean the ensemble averages at each position, not averaging over space. Note that this “average” is no trivial thing. The freely varying variables are no longer &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N&lt;/script&gt; binary variables &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s_i&lt;/script&gt;, but a &lt;em&gt;function&lt;/em&gt; of space, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt;. We are doing infinitely many integrals – let the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; value at each &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt; point vary from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;-1&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1&lt;/script&gt;, and then integrate over all &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;. This is, in fact, a &lt;em&gt;functional integral&lt;/em&gt;. Previously we could still write &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\prod_i \sum_{s_i}&lt;/script&gt; (or in the earlier parts of this course we had &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\int d^{3N} \mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;), but now we must write &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\int Dm(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt; to indicate this is a funcitonal integral.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the Ising model’s translational and rotational symmetry (when viewed on a macroscopic-average level), we know&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g(\mathbf{r_i},\mathbf{r_j})=g(\vert \mathbf{r_i}-\mathbf{r_j}\vert )=g(r)=\langle m(0)m(r)\rangle - \langle m(0)\rangle\langle m(r)\rangle&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The shape of the correlation function is nearly always exponential:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g(r) \sim e^{-\frac{r}{\xi}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt; is a length scale that arises as a parameter in this expression. We call this length the &lt;strong&gt;correlation length&lt;/strong&gt;. It’s the characteristic length over which correlation decay. Its physical meaning is that the magnetization value of two sites more than distance &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt; apart will be totally independent of each other (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g=0&lt;/script&gt;), while two sites within distance &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt; apart will feel the influence of each other (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g&gt;0&lt;/script&gt;) – they want to align with their neighbors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But scaling laws of critical exponents tell us that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi \rightarrow \infty&lt;/script&gt;  at the critical point. At the critical point, the correlation becomes algebraic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g(r) \propto \frac{1}{r^x}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that if the correlation function decays with a given exponent &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt;, a rescaling &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r} \rightarrow b\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt; will change the correlation length accordingly. If, however, the correlation function is algebraic, rescaling will not change the proportionality. This behavior is a manifestation of the fact that the system is &lt;em&gt;scale invariant&lt;/em&gt; at criticality – a conclusion that will arise in the renormalization theory: the critical point is a fixed point of the rescaling, i.e. “renormalization”, transform. To put it more explicitly, an Ising lattice at the critical point is an example of a &lt;em&gt;fractal&lt;/em&gt; structure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ising-correlation-function&quot;&gt;Ising correlation function&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we will show that the Ising correlation function has exactly these properties and mathematical forms we are describing above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways to solve for the correlation function of the Ising model: directly solving a PDE arising from the variational principle, or using renormalization in Fourier space, which is covered in the notes on Gaussian models. Here we focus on the first method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First we use the &lt;em&gt;fluctuation–response theorem&lt;/em&gt; to convert the problem of solving for the correlation function to a different problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Let the magnetic field be a perturbation at origin &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h(\mathbf{r})=h \delta(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt;, then&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{d}{dh} \langle m(\mathbf{r})\rangle\big\vert_{h=0}=-\beta g(r)&lt;/script&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can be proved by explicitly writing the L.H.S. according to the usual &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\frac{\int me^{-\beta H} Dm}{\int e^{-\beta H}Dm}&lt;/script&gt;, pluggin in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H=H_0+\int h(\mathbf{r})m(\mathbf{r})d^d \mathbf{r}=H_0+hm(0)&lt;/script&gt; and switching differentiation and integration, as we always do in statistical mechanics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now our problem becomes to obtain this &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;m(\mathbf{r})\right&gt;\_h %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;: a function depending on the perturbation &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt;. Then we will have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
g(r)=-k_B T \frac{d}{dh} \left&lt;m(\mathbf{r})\right&gt;\_{h=0} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we try approximate this thing, using the &lt;em&gt;saddle point approximation&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\int e^{-\beta H} Dm \approx e^{-\beta H}\big\vert_{m(\mathbf{r})=m_\text{saddle}(\mathbf{r})}&lt;/script&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\text{saddle}(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt; is the function that maximizes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H&lt;/script&gt; among all possible &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This means &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\left&lt;m(\mathbf{r})\right&gt;\approx m_\text{saddle}(\mathbf{r}) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Naturally, we use the variational principle to find the maximum value of the functional &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H&lt;/script&gt;: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;H(m_\text{saddle}+\delta m)-H(m_\text{saddle})=0&lt;/script&gt; for any &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt; to the first order.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This variational equation is a PDE of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;-2k\nabla^2 m + 2r_0 m+4um^3+h\delta(\mathbf{r})=0&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\text{saddle}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h=0&lt;/script&gt;, the solution to this PDE is just &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})=m_0&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0&lt;/script&gt; being still the average spin in Landau theory. So we write &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})=m_0+h\phi(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt;. This way we separate the average and perturbed fluctuations around that average. Also, we now have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g(r)\propto \phi(r)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plugging this into the PDE, we have two Helmholtz equations of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\phi(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt; (depending on the sign of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt;, i.e. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;T-T_c&lt;/script&gt;). Their solutions are known to be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g(r) \propto \phi (r)\propto\frac{e^{-\frac{r}{\xi}}}{r^{d-2}}, \quad \text{for } r \ll \xi&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi^2 =k/r_0&lt;/script&gt; is known from the coefficients of this Helmholtz equation. This is exactly in accordance with the forms of correlation functions above: usually the exponential decay dominates, but at criticality &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi \propto r_0^{-1/2}&lt;/script&gt; diverges and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\exp(-r/\xi)=1&lt;/script&gt; so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g(r)&lt;/script&gt; is algebraic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;critical-exponents-nueta&quot;&gt;Critical exponents &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu,\eta&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\xi \propto t^{-\nu}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;g(r) \propto \frac{1}{r^{d-2+\eta}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we already have the solution of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g(r)&lt;/script&gt;, the rest is easy. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi \propto t^{-1/2}&lt;/script&gt; so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu=1/2&lt;/script&gt; and at the critical point &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g(r) \propto 1/r^{d-2}&lt;/script&gt; so &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\eta=0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;ginzburg-criterion&quot;&gt;Ginzburg criterion&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the crucial approximation we made in MFA and Landau theory? – We assumed spins don’t fluctuate very far from the global average &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0&lt;/script&gt;, and thus discarded the terms of order &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta m^2&lt;/script&gt; compared to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0^2&lt;/script&gt;. We need to know if this approximation is valid, i.e. whether we have&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{ \langle \delta m ^2\rangle} {m_0^2} \ll 1&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the &lt;strong&gt;Ginzburg criterion&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\langle\delta m(\mathbf{r})^2\rangle = \left&lt;m(0)m(r)\right&gt;-\left&lt;m(0)\right&gt;\left&lt;m(r)\right&gt;=g(r) %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;g(r) \rightarrow 0&lt;/script&gt; outside &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt;, so&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\frac{ \langle \delta m ^2\rangle} {m_0^2} \approx \frac{\int_{r&lt;\xi} d^d \mathbf{r} g(r)}{\int_{r&lt;\xi} d^d \mathbf{r}m_0^2}\propto \frac{\xi^2}{m_0^2\xi^d} %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\xi^{2-d}}{m_0^2}\propto \frac{t^{\frac{d-2}{2}}}{t}=t^{\frac{d-4}{2}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now we see why MFA/Landau fails for lower than 4 dimensions: only when &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d\ge 4&lt;/script&gt; will the fluctuation across space be negligible as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t\rightarrow 0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Gaussian Model notes</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Gaussian-model-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Gaussian-model-notes.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-gaussian-model&quot;&gt;The Gaussian model&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have previously obtained the critical exponents in the Landau-Ginzburg model from solving variational equations directly. Now we will see that it is (in some sense) easier to do a Fourier transform on the (simplified) Landau-Ginzburg Hamiltonian and obtain the same results using renormalization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will see that the renormalization procedure in this model is very easy. Another advantage is that by switching to Fourier space, we can turn the function integral &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\int D m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt; –(continuously) infinitely many integrals – into a sum of integrals, because in Fourier space the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{k}&lt;/script&gt;’s are discrete. This is possible because &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m(\mathbf{r})&lt;/script&gt; resides in a function space that’s continuous/smooth enough, and doesn’t actually have as many degrees of freedom as the number of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;’s (uncountable infinite).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;real-space-hamiltonian&quot;&gt;Real-space Hamiltonian&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ignoring the fourth-order term, the Landau-Ginzburg Hamiltonian is (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; is the dimension of the real-space system, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt; is the constant factor parameter and not related to the position vector &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\beta H=\int [(\nabla m(\mathbf{r}))^2+r_0m^2(\mathbf{r})]d^d \mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switch from a continuous &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{r}&lt;/script&gt; to a discrete lattice subscripted by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i,j,\cdots&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_i&lt;/script&gt; be a general order parameter on the lattice site denoted by &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_i&lt;/script&gt; can be visualized as the height of the stack of particles at site &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;i&lt;/script&gt;. The Landau-Ginzburg Hamiltonian can be translated into its equivalent in the discrete lattice:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\beta H = \frac{J}{2} \sum_{&lt;i,j&gt;}(m_i-m_j)^2+r_0 m_i^2 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(Next we can take &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;J&lt;/script&gt; to be 1 because of the irrelevance of a global prefactor multiplying both &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;J&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt;. In this case, it is exactly equivalent to the continuous Hamiltonian.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of Hamiltonian can be interpreted as: 1) having a penalty for the heights &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_i&lt;/script&gt; that take on different values than 0 (the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_i^2&lt;/script&gt; terms); and 2) having a penalty for neighboring heights taking on different values (the gradient or difference squared terms). Thus the lowest energy state is when every &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_i&lt;/script&gt; is equal to 0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fourier-transform&quot;&gt;Fourier transform&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, perform a discrete Fourier transform on &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\{m_i\}&lt;/script&gt;: (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;N&lt;/script&gt; is the number of sites on the lattice)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;m_i=\frac{1}{\sqrt{N}}\sum_{\mathbf{q}}e^{i\mathbf{q}\cdot \mathbf{r}_i}m_\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is easy to show that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_{-\mathbf{q}}=m_{\mathbf{q}}^*&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Explicitly doing the Fourier transform on each term in the discrete Landau-Ginzburg type Hamiltonian gives us&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\beta H=\frac12 \sum_{\mathbf{q}\in \text{BZ}}(q^2+r_0)m_{\mathbf{q}}m_{\mathbf{-q}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q=\vert \mathbf{q}\vert&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Brillouin Zone is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;q_x,q_y,q_z,\cdots \in [-\pi/a,\pi/a]&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Gaussian model has only 1 relevant parameter: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;partition-function-integrating-in-k-space&quot;&gt;Partition function: integrating in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt; space&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_{-\mathbf{q}}&lt;/script&gt; are truly independent, the partition function is given by (note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt; is complex and thus each integral is over the entire &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbb{C}&lt;/script&gt; plane)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Z=\int_{\mathbb{C}^N} \prod_{\mathbf{q}\in \text{BZ}} d^N m_{\mathbf{q}} e^{-\frac12 \sum_{\mathbf{q}}(q^2+r_0)m_\mathbf{q}m_{-\mathbf{q}}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and we can then factorize the entire partition function into&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Z=\prod_{\mathbf{q} \in \text{BZ}}\int_{\mathbb{C}} d m_{\mathbf{q}} e^{-\frac12 (q^2+r_0)m_\mathbf{q}m_{-\mathbf{q}}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_{-\mathbf{q}}=m_\mathbf{q}^*&lt;/script&gt; and they are not independent. If we choose a value for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt;, we have already fixed &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_{-\mathbf{q}}&lt;/script&gt;, too. Thus, we break the Brillouin zone into three parts: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\text{BZ}=\text{BZ}^+ \cup \text{BZ}^- \cup \{0\}&lt;/script&gt;, and only perform the integration for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{q}\in \text{BZ}^+&lt;/script&gt; and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{q}=0&lt;/script&gt;. That is,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Z=\int_{-\infty}^{\infty} dm_0e^{\frac12 r_0 m_0^2} \times \prod_{\mathbf{q} \in \text{BZ}^+}\int_{\mathbb{C}} d m_{\mathbf{q}} e^{- (q^2+r_0)m_\mathbf{q}m_{-\mathbf{q}}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;note that 1) since &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_0&lt;/script&gt; must be real from the conjugate relation, and 2) we no longer integrate over the possibilities of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_{-\mathbf{q}}&lt;/script&gt; but their contribution to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;e^{-\beta H}&lt;/script&gt; is still there, and thus the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;1/2&lt;/script&gt; in front of the Hamiltonian in the last expression has disappeared because they are grouped together with &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt; (the Hamiltonian is invariant under &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{q}\rightarrow -\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m_\mathbf{q}m_{-\mathbf{q}}=\vert m_\mathbf{q}\vert ^2&lt;/script&gt;, and that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\int_\mathbb{C} dz=\int_{-\infty}^\infty \int_{-\infty}^\infty  dxdy=\int_0^\infty 2\pi RdR&lt;/script&gt; for integrands that only depend on &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;R=\vert z\vert&lt;/script&gt;, where &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z=x+iy=Re^{i\theta}, x,y,R,\theta\in \mathbb{R}&lt;/script&gt;, so each integral can be easily evaluated. They are Gaussian integrals (either on the real axis or on the 2D Gaussian integral on the entire plane using polar coordinates, i.e. the method we use to evaluate the 1D Gaussian integral).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus the partition function is calculated to be&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;Z=\prod_{\mathbf{q} \in\text{BZ}}\left(\frac{\pi}{r_0+q^2}\right)^{\frac12}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and therefore&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\ln Z=\frac12 \int_{\mathbf{q} \in \text{BZ}}\ln \left(\frac{\pi}{r_0+q^2}\right) d^d\mathbf{q}&lt;/script&gt;
Again, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt; is the dimension of the system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;correlation&quot;&gt;Correlation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From this, we can show that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\langle m_\mathbf{q}m_\mathbf{q'}\rangle = \frac{1}{q^2+r_0} \delta(\mathbf{q}+\mathbf{q'})&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;from the definition of this quantity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then Fourier transform back into real space and we obtain&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\langle m(\mathbf{r})m(\mathbf{r'})\rangle \propto  \frac{e^{-r/\xi}}{r^{d-2}}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;near criticality and thus know the critical exponent &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\eta=0&lt;/script&gt;, and from the expression of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt; in the Landau Hamiltonian parameters we know &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu=\frac{1}{2}&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;renormalization&quot;&gt;Renormalization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renormalization of the Gaussian model under &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt; space is very simple – just integrate over all the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt; values between the strip (see graphs) and then re-map the &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;k&lt;/script&gt; inside the small square to the entire big square (first Brillouin zone) again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In real space, because of symmetry we must decimate (integrate over) a site between every two sites or perform a “coarse-grain” transform on every four sites. But here, we only need to integrate over a strip of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\mathbf{k}&lt;/script&gt;’s because we have already separated the “fast-varying” and the “slow-varying” components in &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt;. This is very similar to the JPEG compression idea: remove the outer high-frequency components in Fourier space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The renormalization transformation on the only parameter &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0&lt;/script&gt; is &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;r_0'=l^2 r_0&lt;/script&gt;, and thus &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu=1/z=1/2&lt;/script&gt;. Again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other critical exponents then follow from the scaling relations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Renormalization notes</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Critical-exponents-notes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2016/01/24/Critical-exponents-notes.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;h2 id=&quot;critical-exponents-and-renormalization&quot;&gt;Critical exponents and renormalization&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reduced temperature:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;t=\frac{T-T_c}{T_c}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;for-the-ising-model&quot;&gt;For the Ising model:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific free energy &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f(h,T)=F(h,T)/N&lt;/script&gt;, &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;F(h,T)=-k_B T \ln Z&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Order parameter: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m&lt;/script&gt; (magnetization).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specific heat:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;C \propto \frac{\partial^2 f}{\partial T^2}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Source magnetic field: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Susceptibility:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\chi = \frac{\partial m}{\partial h}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Correlation length: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spatial dimension: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;d&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Greek letter&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Definition&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\alpha&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;C \propto t^{-\alpha}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m\propto (-t)^\beta&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\gamma&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\chi \propto t^{-\gamma}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\delta&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;m\propto h^{-\delta}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\nu&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi=t^{-\nu}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\eta&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\langle m(0)m(\mathbf{r})\rangle\propto r^{-d+2-\eta}&lt;/script&gt;&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scaling-laws&quot;&gt;Scaling laws:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\alpha + 2\beta + \gamma = 2&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\gamma = \beta (\delta -1)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\frac{\gamma}{\nu}=2-\eta&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;2-\alpha=d\nu&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among these 6 critical exponents, only 2 are free (we have 4 constraints).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;scaling-dimensions&quot;&gt;Scaling dimensions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we perform a renormalization transform, the parameters in the Hamiltonian change from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;J,K,h,\cdots&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;J',K',h',\cdots&lt;/script&gt;. We can write out this mathematical relation between these two sets of parameters and Taylor expand it around the fixed (critical) point:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\left[\begin{matrix}\Delta J' \\ \Delta K' \\ \Delta h'\end{matrix}\right]=A \left[\begin{matrix}\Delta J \\ \Delta K \\ \Delta h\end{matrix}\right]&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then diagonalize &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among all the eigenvalues and eigenvectors of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;, some &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda_i&gt;1&lt;/script&gt; and thus a little deviation from the fixed point along the direction of this eigenvector will be enlarged after each iteration of renormalization transform. These are called &lt;em&gt;relevant&lt;/em&gt; eigenvalues. Some &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;% &lt;![CDATA[
\lambda_i &lt;1 %]]&gt;&lt;/script&gt; and deviation from the fixed point along this direction will be shrinked back to it. These are called &lt;em&gt;irrelevant&lt;/em&gt;. Those &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda_i=1&lt;/script&gt; are called &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each RG transformation changes the lattice constant from &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;a&lt;/script&gt; to &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;la&lt;/script&gt;, and thus we write each eigenvalue of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt; as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda_i=l^{z_i}&lt;/script&gt;. These &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z_i&lt;/script&gt;’s are called &lt;strong&gt;scaling dimensions&lt;/strong&gt;. A scaling dimension is &lt;strong&gt;relevant&lt;/strong&gt; if it is positive, since we always have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;l&gt;1&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flow diagram, each normalization takes us farther away from the critical point along the &lt;em&gt;relevant&lt;/em&gt; eigenvector direction (the critical point is a &lt;em&gt;repelling&lt;/em&gt; fixed point along this direction) and brings us closer to the critical point along the &lt;em&gt;irrelevant&lt;/em&gt; eigenvector direction (the critical point is an &lt;em&gt;attractive&lt;/em&gt; fixed point along this direction). As for the &lt;em&gt;marginal&lt;/em&gt; case,  the fixed point lies on a line of critical points – a &lt;em&gt;critical line&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;http://gaberber.github.io/images/flow-diagram.png&quot; alt=&quot;flow diagram&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;homogeneity&quot;&gt;Homogeneity&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we obtain the relationship between the scaling dimensions and critical exponents? By arguments of homogeneity, the most important ones of which are the physical observations that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;after each RG transform, the correlation length &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi(J',K')=\xi(J,K)/l&lt;/script&gt; (because if we use coarse grains or decimate intermediate lattice sites, the absolute correlation length remains the same but under the new model with new parameters it should be measured in the new lattice constant &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;la&lt;/script&gt;);&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;and the unit free energy &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f=F/N&lt;/script&gt; becomes &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;f(J',K')=l^d f(J,K)&lt;/script&gt; (because the partition function remains the same for the old and new models and thus a simple relation between the old and new numbers of sites lead to this conclusion).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, since we have diagonalized the transformation matrix &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;, the matrix &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A^n&lt;/script&gt; (i.e. applying the renormalization transformation for &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;n&lt;/script&gt; times) is still diagonal and has eigenvalues &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\lambda_i(l^n)=\lambda_i^n(l)&lt;/script&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;use-renormalization-to-obtain-ritical-exponents&quot;&gt;Use renormalization to obtain ritical exponents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Starting from these homogeneity relations, we can use some tricks (by starting from a point very close to the fixed point and performing the RG transformations many times so that the component along the irrelevant eigenvector shrinks back to 0 and the relevant component becomes 1) to show that&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\xi(l^{ny}s,l^{nz}t)=\frac{\xi(s,t)}{l^n}&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and then&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\xi(s,t)\propto t^{-\frac{1}{z}}\xi(0,1)&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;s, t&lt;/script&gt; are the component of &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;[\Delta J, \Delta K]&lt;/script&gt; in the shrinking eigenvector and growing eigenvector directions, respectively. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y, z&lt;/script&gt; are their respective scaling dimensions. &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;y&lt;/script&gt; is irrelevant and &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z&lt;/script&gt; is relevant. From the flow diagram, we recognize this &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt; here to be proportional to our usual &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;t&lt;/script&gt;, the reduced critical temperature &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;(T-T_c)/T_c&lt;/script&gt;: &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\hat{s}&lt;/script&gt; is the shrinking eigenvector because the stability line has the critical point as its &lt;em&gt;stable fixed point&lt;/em&gt;, i.e. each iteration ends there, while &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\hat{t}&lt;/script&gt; is along the perpendicular direction and magnifies any deviation from the stability line – this is the same as &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;J,K&lt;/script&gt; going toward either the higher temperature or lower temperature direction. (See analysis on the flow diagram at the beginning in the notes.) Thus we have &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\xi\propto t^{-1/z}&lt;/script&gt;. This means&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex; mode=display&quot;&gt;\nu=1/z&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note that &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;z&lt;/script&gt; is a characterizing number that can be calculated from the renormalization transform procedure (by diagonalizing &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;A&lt;/script&gt;). We have thus obtained our first critical exponent. From similar arguments, we can derive &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;\beta=(d-v)/z&lt;/script&gt; (&lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;v&lt;/script&gt; is another relevant scaling dimension that’s related to the magnetic field &lt;script type=&quot;math/tex&quot;&gt;h&lt;/script&gt;) and then all the scaling laws above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;universality&quot;&gt;Universality&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because only the relevant scaling dimensions determine the system’s critical behavior, adding/removing/changing terms that only involve irrelevant scaling dimensions will not change the critical exponents, etc. at all. Thus a whole class of Hamiltonians having the same relevant terms (but different irrelevant terms) all exhibit the same critical behaviors. This phenomenon is called universality. These Hamiltonians belong to one &lt;em&gt;universality class&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 24 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>两个维也纳</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/12/29/vienna.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/12/29/vienna.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;一直都有两个维也纳，莫扎特、约翰施特劳斯的维也纳，和 Klimt、Schiele 的维也纳。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;维也纳和欧洲的大部分城市不一样，非常像中国——建筑和景观的尺度大过北京长安街，气派堪比巴黎，城市在很大程度上属于权力而不是市民；但她又特别欧洲——是巴洛克、洛可可、新古典几个时期建筑的集大成，这一路都是 jaw-dropping 之旅。布拉格的几个巴洛克教堂是宗教界浮夸到极点，这里是属于政治的世俗权力浮夸到了顶点，纽约和拉斯维加斯则是属于商业的世俗权力的顶点。Historical center 附近完全是大帝国首都范，万年以后如果要看欧洲文明辉煌到什么程度，就看巴黎和维也纳就好了。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;然而让维也纳和北京不一样的，除了 Schloss Hofburg 为中心这一系列建筑的风格（希腊罗马的柱式、拉丁语铭文、巨大的穹顶……），还是里面发生过的故事。这些故事属于奥匈帝国两位最著名的君主——Maria Theresa 和 Franz Joseph（还有他老婆茜茜公主），也属于能让这些宫殿以他在此演出为自豪的莫扎特，属于舞曲比河流更出名的蓝色多瑙河和作者约翰施特劳斯。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;金色大厅的演出非常有意思，Lower Austria Orchestra，买票的时候觉得这是什么鬼，结果第一首开场的圆舞曲就给惊艳到了。他们的其他曲目比较平庸，但施特劳斯的这些舞曲实在是驾轻就熟，效果非常好。难怪，Lower Austria 就是维也纳，维也纳就是宫廷，宫廷就是舞曲。我向来不喜欢小施特劳斯和莫扎特这种轻飘飘的毫无内容的宫廷趣味，但当时看着金色大厅这极度浮夸把每个角落都用最夸张最艳丽的金和红交织着堆满的细节，突然就感觉到在这个地方多么轻浮的宫廷趣味都可以被原谅——人类也就在地球上甚至宇宙里创造这么一次文明，在这漫长的一次次倒在半途中的文明积累历程中，如果在最后终于瓜熟蒂落、帝国得成、收获属于文明之秋的丰盛时还不允许我们这么轻浮一次，那也未免太过可悲。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;更何况和金色大厅、美泉宫相同的金色最终孕育出了宫廷以外的另一种金色，如今也藏在一座金灿灿的宫殿 Scholoss Belvedere（美景宫）——Gustav Klimt. 1900 年，维也纳早已厌倦了永恒的轻飘和浮夸，历史没换颜色，但把形状从一切细节都极度对称庄重的宫殿们中抽出，交给了分离派，「从学院分离」，扭曲人体，拥抱情欲。Schiele 和 Klimt 的画是第二个维也纳，这个维也纳可能还有弗洛伊德、卡尔纳普、哥德尔，这个维也纳更像柏林，那个激进的自由的解放的先锋的属于年轻人的柏林，打碎一切的柏林，但这个维也纳不是基尔赫纳的阴惨惨的蓝和绿，而是灿烂的金色。感觉从美景宫出来我对 Klimt 的好感度至少翻了五倍。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;维也纳的「国家 xxx」之类的建筑都极其大（真的非常非常大）和美，然而除了宫廷和「国家 xxx」以外的城市基建很多都显得年久失修，甚至不如布拉格，更遑论荷兰。如果没有第二个维也纳，今天的奥地利人会不会像面对罗马城的近代意大利人一样失落？&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 29 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>捷克</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/12/25/prague.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/12/25/prague.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;来布拉格之前我不知道我们原来曾经在这么多的历史角落和捷克这个国家、布拉格这个城市相遇过，偶然路过卡夫卡博物馆之前我居然不知道这就是卡夫卡居住了一生的城市。然而卡夫卡和布拉格互相概括着彼此，首先从卡夫卡的身世上就能看出一二：他是犹太人，出生于布拉格的老犹太区（彼时已经几乎是一个贫民窟），他的母语是德语（而这座城市说捷克语，一种受罗曼语影响很深的斯拉夫语言，德语是日耳曼语：一座城市集齐了欧洲三大语族）；他出生时是奥匈帝国公民，成为了奥匈帝国官僚机器中的一颗螺丝钉，而他去世时奥匈帝国已经不存在，他的身份是捷克斯洛伐克共和国公民。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;参观布拉格城堡时，我只觉得这里是对「欧洲封建制是典型的古老武士部落简陋传统」的完美诠释，不知道这座城堡的千年历史中，曾经是古波西米亚王国的王宫，也曾是神圣罗马帝国的皇宫；走到一座小书房的时候，看到讲解牌上不认识的词 Window of Defenestration，一眼扫过走出门之后才突然反应过来讲解上说这里是什么：1618 年，正是在这间屋子里，本地的波西米亚新教徒愤怒地将奥匈帝国派来统治的天主教大主教们扔出窗户（他们掉在马粪上所以没摔死，giving a brand new meaning to the words “holy shit”），从此开始了欧洲历史上第三惨烈的大战（仅次于两次世界大战）——三十年战争。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这座城市捷克人（大体上是此地古凯尔特人和斯拉夫人部落演变而成的民族）、日耳曼人、犹太人三族混居，建城史近两千年，老城的建筑动辄有千年历史；布拉格是波西米亚王国的首都，14 世纪时波西米亚王国迎来了自己的查理大帝，建成了今天布拉格游客最密集的地方——查理桥，加冕为神圣罗马帝国的皇帝，布拉格成为神圣罗马帝国首都；这里作为中欧十字路口，近代时来回往复臣服于帝国权力的阴影之下，直到 19 世纪末，捷克斯洛伐克民族成为在接下来的两百年内席卷全球的民族主义「发明民族」运动最典型的代表：于如此纷杂反复的民族、语言、文化、精神性格、政权交相浸染下抽取出一个纵贯千年的波西米亚/捷克民族史，终于创造出一个典型的「民族国家」。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;查理桥，可能是我所见过的最魔幻的桥：它像是把国际象棋棋盘放大百倍，人走在两侧硕大的棋子般圣徒雕像之间，高大的圣徒们、国王们和基督本人各自低头注视着路过的行人；桥两侧各自是童话世界一样的城楼古堡。雕像一直都是我眼中最有魔力的艺术形式，他们可以将你直接从这个现实世界剥离出来，投放到游戏中、电影中、幻想中的中世纪，被古典文明的辉煌遗迹环绕，完全超现实。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这里的第一个宗教改革者 Jan Hus，比马丁路德早了一百年，殉教后波西米亚成为欧洲最早的新教地区之一。三十年战争就开始于捷克新教徒和天主教的奥匈帝国统治者之间的冲突，然而今天，捷克是全欧洲最世俗化的地区：85% 的 atheists/agnostic。捷克和斯洛伐克在上世纪末友好分家，虽然二者有非常相似的历史、文化、语言（捷克语和斯洛伐克语可以互相听懂），但就是因为宗教信仰不同——斯洛伐克 90% 的居民是虔诚的基督徒。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;尽管如此，圣诞夜最著名的地标 Tyn Church 依然举行了一场盛大的弥撒，我也装作能听懂的样子进去参观了（然而这个天主教仪式是用捷克语布道，不知道是不是今天各地已经通行此举不再用拉丁语布道）。这一趟看了不少仍在使用维护的大教堂，最突出的感觉是和佛教的寺庙尤其是西藏的寺庙其实很像很像，完全是同样的 mentality.  但是最大的区别是，弥撒时的音乐是真好听。欧洲如此伟大的音乐传统一发源于教堂里的管风琴和合唱团，二发源于能歌善舞的原始民族 folk music。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这第二个音乐传统，与捷克民族的发明同时觉醒，集大成者就是德沃夏克和斯美塔纳。查理桥上，每天下午钟楼都会奏响那首已经成为这条河流的同义词的 Vltava，回荡在河上，融入这条河的生命。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;布拉格人非常喜欢讲的一个笑话很能反应捷克人的黑色幽默感：捷克斯洛伐克共和国的第一座议会大厦建成之初是捷克爱乐乐团的音乐厅，其揭幕之夜的演出由德沃夏克亲自指挥（德沃夏克热爱美国，写了第九交响曲《自新大陆》，我还听过捷克爱乐在北京现场演奏此作；威尔逊总统也遵照民族自决原则非常爱捷克），然而这栋楼后来被统治捷克的纳粹头子当成了他自己的办公室。他看到楼顶上的一排音乐家雕塑除了巴赫海顿莫扎特贝多芬以外，还有门德尔松这个犹太人，于是下令捷克工人把门德尔松的雕像拆掉。工人们爬上楼之后才发现自己根本不知道哪个人是门德尔松，下去重新问纳粹老大又肯定要挂，于是决定相信聪明的德国人的意见：挨个量每个雕像的鼻子，鼻子最高的那个就是犹太人。结果雕像砸下来以后大家发现，那个是希特勒最崇拜的偶像瓦格纳。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;另一个让人惊讶的事实是：卡夫卡第一次与他的同国同城同胞相遇——他的作品被成规模翻译成捷克语，是 2002 年。在 Velvet Revolution 后之初（对了布拉格的机场就叫哈维尔机场），西方人激动地来这座城市寻找卡夫卡的足迹，然而当地人居然都不知道 Franz Kafka 是谁。因为卡夫卡以德语写作，作品在德国出版，时逢德国表现主义大潮，然而未及获得盛名即迎来了第三帝国的反犹浪潮。纳粹之后，他的作品又再次因为不符合社会主义核心价值观被苏联当局列为禁书。因此直到20世纪末，近百年后，布拉格人才第一次开始认识他们这座城市诞生过的最伟大的作家。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;布拉格是一座一百种风格、一千种思潮、一万种人交汇的十字路口。民族发明运动使得这里最终被打上了「捷克」的标签，然而它实在是欧洲东西南北各种风格的浓缩见证。每道风都从这里吹过，却都没有吹走其他风留下的痕迹。一个最有名的 trivium 是，捷克人不喜欢被称为 Eastern Europeans: 布拉格可是比维也纳还要靠西、还要接近德国。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;这趟算是奥匈帝国圣诞/新年游经典路线吧，布拉格—维也纳—布达佩斯。终于出荷兰了，反正和荷兰很不一样，嗯。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 25 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Nederland</title>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2015/08/29/nederland.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2015/08/29/nederland.html</guid>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;荷兰这个地方真的是美得不像话，景观、建筑、人，都是。来走一走，很容易就能明白为什么荷兰画派的风景和风俗画那么出众（其中的代表人物 Vermeer 正是 Delft 人）。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;对比一下我去过的几个地方，澳洲和欧美一比就是个二流国家，欧美的生活水平相差不大，但荷兰和英语圈的几个移民国家完全不同，在发达国家的行列里跟日本非常像：本国人在本国出生长大工作老去，创造着非常高质量的产品（举一例，如果你对「字体/typography」这件事情眼光比较挑剔、走在街上和观看平面设计产品随时都会注意到字体设计是否合格的话，这里简直就是天堂，美国则是人间，日本是东方的天堂，而中国是妥妥的地狱），过着非常高质量的生活，但外来居民的「融入」这件事情则是基本不可能、他们也完全不在意的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;荷兰有多美？难以用语言描述，照片和视频也很难传达。这里不像是阿尔卑斯山、洛基山那种壮丽而一眼就能俘获你的美，而是当你走在街上时，浑身的每个细胞、眼睛里的每一个细节全都是舒畅的、通透的、刚刚好的。最惹人注目的美应该是建筑——至少是 TU Delft 的建筑，或许跟这里的建筑系相当优秀有关。在清华时见到文图就跟乡巴佬一样各种觉得高大上，去了犹他发现这荒山野岭上的图书馆也不逊色，而这里的图书馆可以直接把前两者轰成渣，甚至在我的眼中略胜耶鲁的两所图书馆。外形和内部都实在是太美了，每次路过都忍不住从各个角度不停地看。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;欧洲和美国很不一样。理想的路径应该是来欧洲交换、去美国上学，可是我跑偏给搞反了。毕业之后留在这里基本不是一个可行的选项，还是得想办法折腾。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;「多元文化」讲座上提到，荷兰和美国文化整体上都是非常接近的，在世界上千万种文化的族谱里，都是属于「西方/欧美/现代」这旗帜鲜明的一支（比如除了西方以外，其他所有主要文化都是集体主义 collectivistic 的，而西方是个人主义 individualistic 的），然而荷兰文化和美国文化在一个方面上有着非常鲜明的区别：在「男性——女性」这一分野下面，美国文化是非常接近「男性」一极的，而荷兰文化非常接近「女性」一极。比如荷兰人全民爱戴的体育明星，都是谦虚、内向、不张扬、邻家男孩女孩型的，而老师当场问一个美国学生「Are American sports stars like this? What will one do in order to be considered an American national hero?」他回答「Drink, party, spend vast amounts of money on flamboyant and stupid things.」美国人的 macho 是盎格鲁文化圈特质、拓殖新大陆的历史、20世纪的战争史和流行文化/大众传媒共同塑造的，而荷兰没有这些。每个来到荷兰的人最先学的两个词都是 lekker 和 gezellig，分别是「好吃/舒服」和「cozy」的意思，和英语里有类似功能的 great 气质完全不同。美国（以及中国）的「越大越好」「更快更高更强」这些想法对荷兰人来说是十分陌生的。&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;世界各国语言里对荷兰王国（Koninkrijk der Nederlanden）这个国家的称呼基本都是「荷兰」这个音（如英语的 Holland），但这其实是不准确的。正确的称呼应该是「尼德兰 Nederland」这个音（如英语的 The Netherlands）。Neder 在英语中盎格鲁化为 nether，意即「下」，Nederland/The Netherlands 直译就是「低地国家」。荷兰语（Dutch）这种语言的历史早于尼德兰这个国家，而在荷兰人逐渐成为海上马车夫、贸易航线延伸至远东和太平洋的年代，今天叫 Nederland 的这片土地还没有成为一个统一的国家，还是像中世纪一样处于四分五裂的状态，周围也没有比利时、德国这些民族国家，彼此之间没有划出明确的边界。虽然不久之后荷兰语民族反抗西班牙统治，一个 The United States of Netherlands 性质的国家成立，但居民的身份认同正如早年邦联时期的美国一样，只知有纽约人、弗吉尼亚人、宾夕法尼亚人，不知有「美利坚合众国人」。因此当世界其他各民族第一次接触到从这片土地上来的船只和商人时，会问他们「你们从哪里来」，而他们会纷纷回答自己的故乡——不是年轻的国名「尼德兰联省共和国」，而是已经延续几百年的各省名。而在尼德兰各省中，80% 的人口集中在西部沿海的北荷兰和南荷兰两个省，阿姆斯特丹、海牙、鹿特丹三大城市（也是主要港口）全在这两省，尤其是绝大多数远洋船只都来自这两个沿海省，因此与外界接触的尼德兰国人几乎全都是荷兰省人，导致大家以为「荷兰」就是「尼德兰」这片土地和国家的称呼。但是 Dutch people（尼德兰人/荷兰国人）中不属于南北荷兰两省的其他省人非常不喜欢被强认成 Holland 荷兰人。&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 29 Aug 2015 13:02:48 +0800</pubDate>
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
